Okay today's דף Daf, יא *daf yud alef* גיטין Gittin. *Gittin* eleven
and we pick up on the משנה Mishnah *mishna* on י עמוד
ב *yud amud bet* and we're continuing to discuss ways in which
גיטין Gittin *gittin* and for women and שטר shtar, שחרור *shtar shichrur*
manumission for a slave are have similarities or possibly differences. So the
משנה Mishnah, *mishna* says as follows כל שטרות shtaras העולים בערכאות של
עובדי כוכבים אף על פי שחותמיהם עובדי כוכבים כשרים *Kol shtaros ha'olim
be'arka'os shel ovdei kochavim af al pi she'chosemim ovdei kochavim kesherim*. All
of the documents, monetary documents that are being processed that have come
out of non-Jewish courts and ערכאות arka'ot, *arka'os* is like an established
court,
even though they are signed by non-Jews, they are כשרים *kesherim*. Shocking,
wow. חוץ chutz מגיטי נשים ושחרורי עבדים *Chutz mi'gittei nashim u'shichrurei avadim*.
With the exception of a גט get, *get* for woman and a
writ of manumission for a slave. That's not surprising. Those are things
that are, you know, one thing is like a monetary issue, this
is something that actually changes personal status and as we know there's
a lot of technical הלכתי Halachic *halachic* requirements about how it's done
which is what the whole מסכת *masechet* is about. So for a
גט get, *get* and a שטר shtar. שחרור *shtar shichrur* of a
slave which is learned out and has from the laws of גיטין
*gittin*, those can are not כשר kosher, *kosher* if they come out
of a non-Jewish court. So okay, that's not surprising at all. What
is surprising is that even these monetary documents are כשר kasher *kosher*
and we'll see why in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*. רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon אומר *Rebbi Shimon omer* and now for even a bigger shocker,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rebbi Shimon* says אף אלו כשרים af elu
kesherim, *af elu kesherim*, even a גט get. *get* for woman and
a שטר shtar. שחרור *shtar shichrur* for a slave are כשר kasher
*kosher* when they come from a non-Jewish court and are signed by
non-Jews. לא Lo, הוזכרו אלא בזמן שנעשו בהדיוט *lo huzkeru ela bizman
shena'asu behedyot*. The only time it's a problem is when they are
done in a private court, but not in an established communal court.
So we'll worry about the הדיוט *hedyot* later, but why how the
heck could this be כשר *kosher*? And not to ruin the surprise,
but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say that is it
because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon's *Rebbi Shimon* holds like רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar *Rebbi Elazar* who holds that עדי מסירה edei mesirah כרתי karty,
*eidi mesirah karshei* that the witnesses that matter for a גט get?
*get* and for שטר shtar. שחרור *shtar shichrur* for a slave are
not the witnesses who sign it, but the witnesses who are present
when it is being handed over and we are dealing with a
case in which it's obvious that those the witnesses signing are not
כשר *kosher* witnesses or non-Jewish witnesses and you'll make sure to have
Jewish witnesses present when it is being handed over. Okay, so that
at least explains the signatures, but the other thing that you have
to assume here is when it says that the document came out
of the court, it doesn't just it mean just that it somehow
was processed by the court, but the actual document was written by
a Jewish סופר *sofer* with the right intent, all the הלכות halachos
*halachos* being followed and so on. So the real חידוש chiddush *chidush*
here is about the signatures, the document itself everything else was being
done properly. Okay, that's as far as a גט get *get* and
based on the principle of עדי מסירה aidei mesira כרתי *eidi mesirah
karshei*. Now let's go back and look at why the first part
of the משנה Mishna *mishna* about why a monetary document is כשר
*kosher*. So let's see what the
משנה Mishna *mishna* says, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says
as follows, it says קפסיק ותני *kapasik ve'tani* that the
משנה Mishna *mishna* sort of
makes is
categorical, you
know makes no distinctions, לא שנא מכר ולא שנא מתנה *lo shna
mecher lo shna matana*. When it says
a monetary document
with from a
non-Jewish court is כשר *kosher*, it does not distinguish makes no
distinction it doesn't matter if it's for a sale or for a
gift. בשלמא מכר *bishlama mecher*, I can understand a document that attests
to a sale מדייב זוזי קמיהו דקנה *mi'dihiv zuzei kaminai hu dekana*
because we as I mentioned one way to transfer ownership is for
real estate is by paying for it and the assumption here is
is that the non-Jewish court system would never have written a document
of ownership had it not been paid for. So therefore you will
only be seeing this document after it has been paid for and
therefore the act of acquisition halachically occurred through the paying of money
and therefore this document coming from the non-Jewish court is only attesting
to the fact that
to
you know is is to the fact that
The court if money had not been given in their presence to
purchase the field, they never would have agreed to write the document.
So the fact that this document is coming out of an established
non-Jewish court is absolute evidence that this sale took place. Okay? So
therefore that's fine, even if doesn't satisfy normal halakhic requirements of a
שטר, shtar you know, it is totally valid as a source of
evidence. It's like there was a videotape. You know, it's not working
qua שטר, shtar it's working because a court would never have issued
this had this not definitely occurred, so we can absolutely use this
as evidence that this occurred. That's the way almost all the ראשונים
Rishonim understand it. Some want to frame it in the sense of
it's a rabbinic תקנה, takkana, but even without a rabbinic תקנה, takkana,
you can distinguish between evidence and something that is formal testimony. For
example, the time of the ראשונים, Rishonim, they were
in אשכנז Ashkenaz where women were involved in business, they would often
accept a women's testimony on things in monetary matters, not as formal
עדות eidus as testimony, but as evidence. You know, we're just going
to treat it as solid evidence that this occurred. Okay, so that's
fine. All we need is evidence and this can function as evidence,
even if it's not a formal שטר. shtar, Okay? אלא מתנה, Ella
matana, but by a gift, במאי קקני, b'mai kakani, how would you
acquire this piece of property as a gift? Right, it's only, you
know, through the handing over of a שטר. shtar Maybe it's by
an act of חזקה, chazaka, but there's no reason to think that
that, you know, that's what this non-Jewish court is attesting to. So
therefore, presumably, it's by this שטר. shtar Well, how can this שטר
shtar, function this way? That has to be an instrument and it
is not a formal שטר shtar? because it is not done through
a Jewish court with Jewish witnesses. So במאי קקני, b'mai kakani, the
only way to acquire it is with this שטר, shtar, והאי שטר
חספא בעלמא הוא, v'hai shtar chaspa b'alma hu, and this שטר shtar
is like a piece of pottery, it's worthless as that type of
an instrument.
דאמר שמואל דינא דמלכותא דינא. D'amar Shmuel dina d'malchusa dina. So שמואל
Shmuel says that this is part, you're right, technically that shouldn't work,
but it works because it works in secular law and the law
of the sovereign is the law. And this is of course a
major halakhic principle, דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina d'malchusa dina. There's a major
debate in the ראשונים Rishonim and the אחרונים Achronim what the scope
of it is. But שמואל Shmuel is saying something that I think
we probably have incorporated, but certainly, you know, it's assumed to apply
in a wide range of monetary matters. And if you just think
about our normal life, right, when you go ahead and you buy
something in a store, right, you're not starting to wonder about like
have you actually taken possession of it halakhically and do you really
own it and can you really use it because, you know, maybe
you didn't do משיכה meshicha or הגבהה hagba or whatever the case
might be. We assume that the ways in which society recognizes that
ownership transfers is halakhically binding. You know, there are other devices to
explain why that's true, but anyway, דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina d'malchusa dina,
that's what שמואל Shmuel said, and yes, that does transfer the property.
ואיבעית אימא תני חוץ מגיטי נשים ושחרורי עבדים, v'iba'is eima tani chutz
migitei nashim v'shichrurei avadim, for some reason you don't want to make
recourse to דינא דמלכותא דינא dina d'malchusa dina or maybe the scope
of דינא דמלכותא דינא dina d'malchusa dina is a little bit more
narrow, which we won't discuss here, then the way to explain the
משנה Mishna, is when it says everything works except a גט, get
it doesn't just mean a גט, get it means
the category of גט. get
נתנאל, Netanel, נתנאל, Netanel, I'm recording something so please don't make a
lot of clanging, okay?
Sorry about that ambient noise there. What's the category of גט? get?
The category of גט get? is a שטר that functions as an
instrument. So therefore, שטרות that come from non-Jewish courts can work when
they are evidence, they cannot work when they are/serve as instruments, like
a גט get, and a writ of manumission, and this would also
occur to apply to a document for transferring of property, a שטר
מתנה. shtar matana. Okay, that's the first part of the משנה, Mishna.
fascinating why the secular ones work, why the monetary ones work. Now
we have to get to the shocking position of רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon. about why a גט get works. So רבי שמעון אומר אף
אלו כשרים, Rabbi Shimon omer af elu k'sherim, even a גט get.
is kosher. Again, we're going to assume that the writing was all
done properly, but the signatures are not Jewish. How could that work?
והא לאו בני כריתות נינהו, v'ha lo bnei krisus ninu, says the
גמרא, Gemara one minute, how could signatures of non-Jews make a functional
גט? get Non-Jews are not in the category of כריתות, krisus, right?
Which is like ספר כריתות sefer krisus when the תורה Torah describes
a book of division of divorce. So since they're not in our
הלכות of marriage and divorce, how can they create this proper instrument
to serve to effect a divorce? Now by the way, you might
want to say what do you mean, you know, there's even a
more basic reason why they shouldn't be able to make a document,
you know, why the גמרא Gemara had to go to its whole
explanation before, because they can't actually also be good witnesses, they're not
halakhic witnesses. So תוספות Tosafos says that, if you look at תוספות
Tosafos והא לאו בני כריתות נינהו, v'ha lo bnei krisus ninu, תוספות
Tosafos says הוי מצי למיפרך הא לאו בני עדות נינהו, havi matzi
limifrach ha lo bnei eidus ninu, it could have also said that
they are not good witnesses, but it's saying here that they cannot
do it, you know, besides that because they cannot make this type
of an instrument because they're not in the category of marriage and
divorce. I should point out... mention that there are actually some ראשונים
Rishonim that raise the possibility that non-Jews if we address the concern
of whether they're telling the truth or not, maybe technically could be
good witnesses, which is shocking. Discuss that a little bit tomorrow on
the on דף יב. Daf Yud Bet. Okay. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this: So how can that be? How can they
make a good גט? get, So
אמר רבי זירא Amar Rabbi Zeira says רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, אמר
רבי שמעון לשיטתו דרבי אלעזר דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי. Amar Rabbi Shimon
le-shitato de-Rabbi Elazar de-amar edei mesirah karty. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon. descended
into like he dived deep into the position of רבי אלעזר Rabbi
Elazar that says that the witnesses who are at the handing over
of the גט, get. right, there's עדי חתימה edei chatimah when it's
signed and עדי מסירה when it's handed over, the witnesses that are
there when the גט get. is being handed over, they are the
ones that are כרתי, like the same word of בני כריתות, bene
krisus, they are the one that make it a divorce, that make
it effective, that make it a good גט. get So that's the
witnesses that matter. So it doesn't really matter that the witnesses are
non-Jews, assuming the גט get was done properly, the writing was properly
as long as you have the right witnesses when it's being handed
over. Okay, well now you got to make sure you do have
those right witnesses. The גמרא Gemara is going to say this is
a little bit of a dangerous document because it's signed by invalid
witnesses. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says והאמר
רבי אבא מודה רבי אלעזר במזויף מתוכו שפסול. Ve-ha-amar Rabbi Abba: Modeh
Rabbi Elazar bi-mzuyuf mi-tocho she-pasul. But one minute, didn't רבי אבא Rabbi
Abba say that רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar agreed that when something was
considered forged from within it's invalid? Now this is not actually forged,
but the point is it's one thing not to have something, it's
another thing to have it and to have it being false or
wrong. So okay, you don't have witnesses on your גט, get that's
good for רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar if you have physical witnesses present.
But if you actually have non-kosher witnesses signing it, that should be
a basis for invalidity. What's the reason for it that it should
be invalid? Because you might come to rely on these witnesses. This
looks like a totally valid גט. get. Now what does that mean
you might come to rely on them? Well, there it depends. According
to some ראשונים Rishonim for רבי אלעזר even though you can suffice
with just the witnesses when it's handed over, but some ראשונים Rishonim
say if you don't have those witnesses, you could also use the
witnesses who signed on the גט. get So from that perspective, it's
very clear why this גט Get is a real danger
because it's signed by non-Jews and you might just rely on them
and hand it over without any Jewish witnesses present. Other... so that's
again a rabbinic problem. Halachically it would be fine, but it's a
very dangerous document and the rabbis would invalidate it rabbinically because you
could wind up using it without witnesses present. An alternative would be
even if you assume you always need witnesses present, you'll see these
signatures on the document, John Smith, and then you'll say, hey, is
John Smith, is there a John Smith here? Oh, and there and
so-and-so here, and you'll get those people to be the witnesses when
it's handed over. Now you might say, well, you'll see that they're
non-Jews, but it's very clear in the גמרא Gemara that in the
time of the גמרא Gemara it was not immediately evident who was
Jewish and not Jewish by any external markers. So therefore it is
a dangerous document. You might use it alone or you might use
the witnesses on it to be the ones that are standing there.
And therefore how can we validate a document with signatures of non-Jews
rabbinically? So the גמרא Gemara. says הכא מאי עסקינן? hacha mai askinan?
What are we talking about? Top of יא עמוד א. Yud Alef
Amud Alef. בשמות מובהקים. Bi-shemos muvhakim. That
these names are clearly clearly the names of non-Jews and therefore there
is no concern. So it's signed by Chris Christopherson. Okay, you know,
and Luka Macpherson or something. So in those cases you know they're
not Jewish names and therefore you will never rely on them by
themselves, you'll never use those people to be the witnesses. It's clear
it was non-Jews and therefore you can go ahead and make sure
to get Jewish witnesses and it'll be fine. היכי דמי שמות מובהקים?
Heichi dami shemos muvhakim? What's an example of these types of clearly
non-Jewish names? אמר רב פפא כגון הורמיז ואבודינא בר שיבתאי ובר קידרי
ובאטי וניקמונא. Amar Rav Pappa: Kegon Hurmiz va-Avudina bar Shiptai u-var Kidri
u-Bati ve-Nakimuna. Okay,
so those are the names, some very clear non-Jewish names, and if
those types of names are there, the document is okay because those
signatures do not invalidate it and you'll just make sure to get
good kosher Jewish witnesses when you hand it over. אבל שמות שאין
מובהקים מאי? Aval shemos she-ein muvhakim mai? But the גמרא Gemara says
okay, but then what would you be saying if the names were
not clearly non-Jewish names? Signed by non-Jews but you know maybe they're
Jewish names. Or maybe they were Jews who signed it. What would
you say? לא, you would say you couldn't use it for the
reasons we said, because then you might wind up using a document
with non-Jewish signatures without getting Jews to be present. אי הכי, I
hachi, if that's true, אדדתני סיפא לא הוזכרו אלא בזמן שנעשו בהדיוט.
ad de-tani seifa: Lo huzkeru ela bi-zeman she-na’asu be-hedyot. When the סיפא
seifa says רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon statement that it's only a problem
when it's in a private court, ליפלוג וליתני בדידי. livlog ve-lisni be-didi.
He should have made a distinction about the case itself of when
he is saying it's kosher in an ערכאות, arkaot in an established
court. He should have been very clear that he's limiting himself to
case of clearly not Jewish names. ליפלוג וליתני בדידי במה דברים אמורים
בשמות מובהקים. Livlog ve-lisni be-didi: Be-meh devarim amurim, bi-shemos muvhakim.
When am I saying it's good if it comes from an established
court? If there are names that are clearly non-Jewish names. אבל שמות
שאין מובהקים לא. Aval shemos she-ein muvhakim, lo.
Names that are not clearly non-Jewish, no, it's not good. Right, if
that's one of your core criteria, then you should. It should say
that that is what is required for this גט get to be
good. So the גמרא Gemara says הכי נמי קאמר, Hachi nami ka'amar,
yeah, that's what the משנה Mishna really is saying. במה דברים אמורים,
Bamei devarim amurim,
when is this true? Where was I?
הכי נמי קאמר. Hachi nami ka'amar. I just lost my place. במה
דברים אמורים בשמות מובהקים, Bamei devarim amurim beshemot muvhaqim, when there are
expert names. אבל בשמות שאינם מובהקים, Aval beshemot she'einam muvhaqim, names that
are not clearly not Jewish, נעשה כמי שנעשו בהדיוט ופסולין. na'aseh kemishe'nasu
behedyot upesulin.
Then it's like it was done in, you know, done in a
private court and it's invalid. Now, that's a very poor read of
the משנה Mishna. because we haven't even mentioning private court. We're saying
a big חידוש that this type of a גט is כשר, so
therefore in that type of case, you would think you would have
to say explicitly only in the following cases when these names are
clearly not Jewish names. But the גמרא Gemara, wants to read that
in to saying, oh, in a private court it's not good, you
know, and like not expert names is also sort of is also
like a private court, so that's also not good. Okay, so it's
sort of what we call עיקר חסר מן הספר; ikar chaser min
hasefer; you're sort of not saying what's the core criterion here. But
anyway, be that as it may, it is saying that yes, that
is how we're going to limit the statement of רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon Now, why by the way in a private court is it
not good is not clear. רש"י Rashi has a whole and תוספות
Tosafot have a whole explanation that says that's not talking about a
גט. A גט actually would be okay in a private court. Anyway,
it's very complicated. It's not the simplest way to read the גמרא.
Gemara The simplest way to read the גמרא Gemara, is what the
ר"ן Ran says. The ר"ן Ran says that there really are now
two criteria. It has to be a clearly non-Jewish name and it
has to be a public established court. Both things combined will make
it very well known that it was signed by non-Jews. Okay, but
if it is in one or not, but if you don't have
both of them, then you're afraid that you know, it won't be
clearly known enough and you'll come to rely on it. According to
the ר"ן's Ran read, it's a little bit better the way the
גמרא Gemara tries to fit it into the משנה Mishna. because the
problem of a private court is also that it's not clear enough
it's being done by non-Jews. Okay, a big public major central court
system, like that gives makes everybody clear, oh wait a minute, this
was done by the non-Jewish court, probably was done by non-Jews, signed
by non-Jews, and so on. So both of those now are pretty
central criteria and that's really the point of the משנה, Mishna. that
you need all those things to make sure that it's clear that
it was signed by non-Jews. Okay. ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, says the
גמרא, Gemara and if you want I can tell you, סיפא אתא
לגיתי ממון. seifa ata legitei mammon. The last statement, oh, a private
court is not good, is talking about a monetary document and that's
not good because there's concerns about whether you can it's as trustworthy
as one that comes from a public court. You know, it goes
back to the first part of the משנה. Mishna It's not part
of the statement of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon The first part of
the משנה Mishna says monetary documents in ערכאות arkaot. are good, but
in private courts they're not good. Okay, fine. But at the end
of the day then, the basic requirement that it be a clearly
non-Jewish name is not being stated in the משנה. Mishna
But okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
והכי קאמר, Ve'hachi ka'amar, here's how it would read. לא הוזכרו גיתי
ממון דפסולין אלא זמן שנעשו בהדיוט. Lo huzkeru gitei mammon depesulin ela
zeman shena'asu behedyot. The reading the last part of the statement not
as רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon but going back to the first part
of the משנה. גיתי ממון Gitei mammon are good, גיתין gittin are
not good, parentheses, רבי שמעון Shimon says they're good, back to גיתי
ממון, gitei mammon, even when we said גיתי ממון gitei mammon are
good, that's only in public courts, not in private courts. Okay. תניא.
Tanya. Now we're going to quote a ברייתא Beraita where רבי שמעון
Shimon is going to push his case
against the חכמים Chachamim to say that גיתין gittin are good when
they are done in the ערכאות. Arkaot, So we done in the
ברייתא, Beraita, אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי יוסי כך אמר רבי שמעון לחכמים
Amar Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Yose kach amar Rabbi Shimon lachachamim in צידן,
Tzidan, לא נחלקו רבי עקיבא וחכמים על כל השטרות העולים בערכאות של
עכו שאף על פי שחותמיהן עכו כשירים lo necheleku Rabbi Akiva vechachamim
al kol hashtarot ha'olim be'arkaot shel Akko she'af al pi shechosemeihen Akko
kesherim and ואפילו גיתי נשים ושחרורי עבדים. ve'afilu gitei nashim veshichrurei avadim.
He says, look, there's a debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
the חכמים Chachamim about this. We didn't even know that. But he's
saying but that debate never applied to public courts. Okay, documents signed
by non-Jews in the public courts, those documents everybody always agreed they
were כשר and not only monetary documents, even גיתין gittin and, you
know, writs of manumission for slaves, they're all כשר just like רבי
שמעון Shimon says in our
משנה. לא נחלקו אלא בזמן שנעשו בהדיוט. Lo necheleku ela bizeman shena'asu
behedyot.
The only time there was a disagreement was when things were done
in private courts. שרבי עקיבא מכשיר וחכמים פוסלין. sheRabbi Akiva machshir vechachamim
poslin. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that that's okay, he's not worried
about the trustworthiness of those documents. We're talking about let's say monetary
documents, but the חכמים Chachamim are saying no no no, private courts
we are worried about those the trustworthiness of those documents, so there
there is a debate. חוץ מגיתי נשים ושחרורי עבדים, chutz migitei nashim
veshichrurei avadim,
except for גיתין gittin and שחרורי עבדים. shichrurei avadim. Now does the
חוץ go on the חכמים Chachamim invalidate except for that case or
on the רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva? Again this is the debate of
רש"י, Rashi, תוספות Tosafot on one side, the ר"ן Ran on the
other. I'm going to read it like the ר"ן, Ran, which is
clear much easier read of the משנה of the גמרא, Gemara which
is in those private courts, by the way, there the חכמים Chachamim
say yes, I mean רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says yes they are
good, the חכמים Chachamim say no they're not good. That's by monetary
documents. But of course everybody would agree that the private in the
private courts גיתין gittin are not good. Okay, that makes sense, right?
Because right now גיתין gittin are clearly the ones that are much
more questionable. Why they should be good. So in the public court,
nobody disagrees, everything is good, even גיטין. In the private courts, there's
a debate, a debate of monetary documents, but there, but of course
there גיטין would be no good. That is not debated. Okay. Okay.
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, now רבן
שמעון Rabban Shimon says אף אלו כשרים,
you know what? I am going to allow a גט even in
a private court. How can you do this? Aren't you concerned that
people won't know that they're signed by non-Jews and all the concerns
we mentioned before? So the גמרא Gemara says במקום שאין ישראל חותמים,
bemakom she'ein Yisrael chotmim, if it's a type of a court where
they do not allow Jews to sign. So in some municipalities, Jews
were not allowed to sign, you know, the official government
documents that were done in the secular courts. So in those municipalities,
he's saying I will even allow it in a private court. You'll
know it's signed by non-Jews and there's no concern. אבל במקום שישראל
חותמים לא, aval bemakom she'Yisrael chotmim lo,
but if Jews are allowed to sign, then I'm agreeing private court
there's too much of a concern it won't be clear that it's
a non-Jew. So again, you need two
things the way the ר"ן Ran reads it you need two things
for it to be clear that it's a non-Jew and to allow
this document: a very clear non-Jewish name and done in a public
court. But in a private court, we're concerned that you won't be
aware. Says רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel, even in
a private court in places where non-Jews are not allowed to sign...
where Jews are not allowed to sign, I am not concerned that
you won't be aware because there obviously the only people who would
sign would be non-Jews. So I will even allow private court if
Jews are not allowed to sign in that region. Says גמרא Gemara
says במקום שאין ישראל חותמים נמי ליגזור אטו מקום שישראל חותמים,
bemakom she'ein Yisrael chotmim nami ligzor
atu makom she'Yisrael chotmim,
why don't we make a גזירה Gzeira that you can't allow a
document in a place where Jews are not allowed to sign because
if we allow those types of documents, you'll come to allow documents
in places where Jews are allowed to sign? So the גמרא Gemara
says שמא בשמא מיחלף אתרא באתרא לא מיחלף. shma bishma michelaf atra
batra lo michelaf. No,
look, we could understand people that might debate whether you can or
you know whether the idea of like of a well-known non-Jewish name
is good or not because, you know, it's not exactly clear what's
a clear non-Jewish name, what's an ambiguous name, you know, what exactly
is the line between that? So maybe you don't want to allow
non-Jewish names, clearly non-Jewish names, because that'll be
too... because that'll be too easy to come to allow names that
are not clearly non-Jewish. But locations, municipality because, you know, it's like
there's no clear line there. But in a municipality where non... where
Jews are not allowed to sign, there is no ambiguity. So therefore
that he'll be more okay with. And one way that seems like
the גמרא Gemara is saying it is he might not even have
had so much of a criteria about the nature of the names.
For him the whole criteria might have been the region. If not...
if Jews are not allowed to sign, then everybody knows the signatures
are non-Jews and those documents are okay. Public courts, private courts, I
don't care. Clearly Jews did not sign it. And that's very black
and white. But I'm not going to start playing around with how
obvious are the names Jewish or non-Jewish, that's very vague. Okay.
רבינא סבר, Ravina savar, now we're going to move on to a
practical discussion. רבינא סבר לאכשורי בכנופיא דארמאי. Ravina savar l'achshurei b'knufya d'Armai.
Ravina thought to allow, presumably now we're talking about a monetary
document, and remember those are good in pub... in the public courts,
not in private courts. And he allowed in a type of a
case where there was a large communal gathering of the non-Jews like,
you know, and maybe they set up an ad hoc court, it
wasn't an ערכאות, Arkaot but it was a, you know, it was
something that was public. Like the גמרא Gemara says how, you know,
whatever about how they would have regular or the משנה of how
they have regular courts on Mondays and Thursdays, you know, in the
villages when everybody would gather for the market day. So this would
be something like that. But it wasn't an established court and he
thought that was close enough and he was going to allow that
document.
אמר ליה רפרם, Amar lei Rafram, so רפרם Rafram pushed back and
said ערכאות תנן. Arkaot tnan. No, the משנה says an ערכאות which
means a fixed established court and that is what is required. Okay.
אמר רבא האי שטר פרסאה דמסרי ניהליה באפי סהדי ישראל. Amar Rava
hai shtar Parsaa de'masri nihaleh b'apei sahadei Yisrael. If you have a
Persian document that was handed over in the presence of Jewish witnesses.
Now it's going to seem from context that what we're talking here
is about a document testifying to a loan. ראובן Reuven borrowed a
thousand dollars from שמעון and it's signed... it's written in Persian, signed
by Persian witnesses, handed over in front of Jews. Now what good
is a document like that normally? Not a Persian one, a normal
הלכתי Halachic one. A normal הלכתי document like that is good because
you can (a) use it to prove that the money was borrowed,
(b) use it to prove that the money hasn't been paid back
yet because if it had been paid back yet, why am I
still holding on to the document unless you have a receipt to
prove against that? And (c) when something is written in a document,
it is... it becomes a matter of public record and that gives
me a lien on your property. So if after you borrow the
money from me, somebody buys your property, real estate we're talking about,
then I can go ahead and I can take that property if
you don't have money on your own possession. Okay, and that can
only be, now that's not fair to the person buying property from
you if he's not aware of it. So that's why it needs
to
be... So here, there are witnesses present with this Persian document handing
over that's being said that you borrowed a thousand dollars from me.
And we're going to say the document is good. Now, who needs
the document to be good? If the witnesses know what's happening, just
rely on the witnesses. So that's not fully spelled out, but it
seems that the witnesses, they might not remember a year from now
or ten years from now, they might not remember the details unprompted,
they might not remember at all unprompted, or they might not remember
the details: was it a thousand, was it ten thousand, what exactly
was the date, what exactly was the conditions? So therefore, but because
they're seeing the document, and then when the document is produced ten
years from now, they could say yes, we remember, that was the
document that was handed over, and therefore their memory of the document
plus the document makes that document valid, okay? So that's how that's
going to work and now that can function as a good document,
even though it's written in Persian and signed by non-Jewish witnesses.
So האי פרסטק פרסאה דמסרי ניהליה באפי סהדי ישראל, Hai parstak parsa'ah
demasrei nihalei be'apei sahadei Yisrael, and with this document that was handed
over in the presence of Jewish witnesses, מגבינן ביה מבני חורי, Magbinan
beih mibnei chorei, you can use it to collect from unencumbered property,
meaning I can now collect from שמעון property he has on his
own person, but I cannot, it does not give me liens, I
cannot collect from property that he has sold, real estate that he
has sold, because since it's not a הלכה halachic שטר, it
does not create liens. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to
say one minute, how does this work? והא לא ידעי למיקריה, Veha
lo yadei lemikrarei, the witnesses that saw it handed over, they can't
read Persian, so how do they know what they're testifying to? So
the גמרא Gemara says בדידעי, Bedidyei, no, we're talking about a case
that they do know how to read Persian and they read it
and they are witnessing it and they're agreeing that that is exactly
what has occurred, what it's stating is what occurred. Okay, והא בעינן
כתב שאינו יכול להזייף וליכא, Veha bayinan ktav she'eino yachol lehizayef veleika,
don't you need a type of writing that cannot be forged? Meaning
it has to be written on a type of parchment with a
type of ink that, were you to erase the ink, you would
see that something had been erased. There's an obvious reason why you
need this. This document says שמעון borrowed a thousand dollars from
דוב. Dov. So after I get that document in my possession, I'll
just erase it and instead of a thousand write a million. By
the way, you know, that's why on a check, if people remember
what checks are, it's not only a place to write the number
but also you write it out in words, one thousand dollars, because
if you just wrote one thousand you could squeeze in an extra
zero or an extra one or something like that. Okay, so you
need something that cannot be forged and this seems to assume that
a standard Persian document was able to be erased and to be
forged. Of course, one wonders how anybody could have managed in a
system like that, but okay, that's what the גמרא Gemara asks. So
since that's the case, how could their testimony combined with this document?
So
the גמרא Gemara says בדפיצא, Bedafitza, no, you have actually treated the
parchment with this gallnut and actually yes, it was done
on a type of a paper, a parchment that could not be
forged. So the גמרא Gemara says והא בעינן תורץ שיחזור מעניינו של
שטר בשיטה אחרונה, Veha bayinan toretz sheyachzor meinyano shel shtar beshita acharona,
don't we have a principle that you have to repeat the
essence of the document in the last line? This means if you
like know by a כתובה, ketubah, it says
וקנינא מכל מה דכתב ומפורש לעילא במנא דכשר למקניא ביה והכל שריר
וקיים. Vekanyana mikol mah dektav umforash le'eila bemana dechasher le'makanya beih vehakol
sharir vekayam. We sort of did a קנין kinyan on everything we
said above and everything is done properly. What's the purpose of that
line? The purpose of that line is you want to know where
the end of the document is, because you don't want witnesses to
sign and leave enough of a space between the end and their
signature that somebody could squeeze in another line and say, oh plus
he borrowed another million dollars. So therefore what you do is the
very last line of the document essentially says this is the last
line of the document, okay? That's what הכל שריר וקיים Hakol sharir
vekayam is doing. So you need that statement, this is the last
line of the document, to say anything afterwards is no good, and
that's not the case here, so why shouldn't we be afraid that
something will be squeezed in underneath? So the גמרא Gemara says במהדר,
Bimahadeir, yes, they made it fit that criteria as well. So you've
got this Persian document, all of the technical requirements that we're concerned
about about the document being misused, it's still a non-Jewish document, but
all those technical requirements we have are all being satisfied and the
עדים aidim know how to read it and therefore they can testify
to it and you can use it. So the גמרא says אי
הכי, I hachi, if it's such a perfect document, ממשעבדי נמי, Mimishabdei
nami, so why not collect from, why not have liens, because why
doesn't it create liens if it's such a perfect document? So the
גמרא says לית ליה קלא, Leit lei kala, because even though now
you basically have עדי מסירה plus a perfect document, why don't they
combine to make a real שטר? So the גמרא says it might
be halachically a שטר, but because it is not a Jewish שטר
and signed by Jewish witnesses, there is not enough of a public
record of it or public knowledge of it that it would be
fair to have that create a lien. Okay, let's one last discussion
around going back to גט and around non-Jewish signatures. בעי מיניה ריש
לקיש מרבי יוחנן, Ba'ei minei Reish Lakish meiRabbi Yochanan, ריש לקיש Reish
Lakish asked from רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, important to remember ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan are both... In ארץ ישראל
*Eretz Yisrael*, okay, עדים החתומים על הגט ושמותיהם כשמות עובדי כוכבים *Edim
ha-chatumim al ha-get u-shmoteihem ki-shmotei ovdei kochavim*. So we were talking about
you know non-Jews signed it, can you use it? Now we're talking
about at the receiving end, you have a גט *get* that's being
delivered and you're looking at the signatures here, in your court system,
wherever it's coming from, and coming let's say from one place of
Israel to another, we'll see that be relevant in a minute. And
the signatures, they look like non-Jewish signatures. So you now have a
question. What is the story here? Are these signatures of Jews that
just happen to have non-Jewish sounding names? If that's the case, this
גט *get* is good. Or is this the signatures of non-Jews? In
which case the גט *get* is no good because even if you
were then to bring over some Jews to be present in the
handing over, because the names are ambiguous, remember the rabbi said you
can't use that document. It could be misused. So if it's non-Jews
with possibly Jewish, possibly not-Jewish names, it's no good because it's a
dangerous document. If however it happens to be Jews, nobody said you
can't use documents signed by Jews if they happen to have non-Jewish
names. So what should we assume? Should we assume this was signed
by Jews and it's good, or should we be concerned it was
signed by non-Jews and it's not good? So the גמרא *Gemara* says
אמר ליה *Amar leih*, so רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said back to
him, לא בא לידינו אלא לוקיס ולוס והכשרנו *Lo ba l'yadeinu ela
Lukis v'Lus v'hichsharnu*. The only case we ever had was a dock
like this, was a document signed by somebody called Lucas and Lus,
or Luke, I don't know, and Lus, and we said it was
good. But the way תוספות *Tosafot*, drastic תוספות *Tosafot* explains is those
were clearly non-Jewish names so that gets back to our משנה *Mishna*.
We assumed it was non-Jewish but because it was so clearly non-Jewish,
it was not a problematic document and we had Jews present at
the handing over. Okay. But ambiguous names, like I don't know what
the answer is. So the גמרא *Gemara* says ודווקא *V'davka*, or not
I don't know what the answer is, but actually it's not good.
ודווקא לוקס ולוס דלא שכיחי ישראל דמסקי בשמייהו *V'davka Lukos v'Lus d'la
shechichi Yisrael d'maski bishmayhu*. Only Lucas and Lus where it is not
at all common that Jews would use that name and therefore we
know it's non-Jewish names and we'll make sure that there are Jews
present at the handing over. אבל שמהתא אחריני *Aval shemata achrinei*, other
names, this is really what the גמרא *Gemara* is commenting on רבי
יוחנן's *Rabbi Yochanan's* statement. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* is not saying this.
אבל שמהתא אחריני דשכיחי ישראל דמסקי בשמתייהו *Aval shemata achrinei d'shcheichi Yisrael
d'maski bishmateihu*, that it's common that Jews might use some type of
names that are a little like, you know, they sound non-Jewish but
we know that Jews do use those names. In those type of
cases where there's ambiguity whether they're Jewish or non-Jewish, in those types
of cases לא *Lo*, you can't use them. Right? Because if they're
Jews, if you knew they were Jews you could use it, but
because it might be non-Jewish and because it's not clear that they're
non-Jewish, that's a problem. איתיבי *Eiteivei*. So now let me challenge this
statement that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* sort of said that, you know,
ambiguous names are not good because they might be non-Jewish. גיטין *Gittin*,
we have a תוספתא *Tosefta* that teaches the following: גיטין הבאים ממדינת
הים והעדים חתומים עליהם *Gittin ha-ba'im mi-medinat ha-yam v'ha-edim chatumim aleihem*. You
have גיטין *Gittin* that come from overseas, not from within Israel, that'll
be relevant. And there are witness signatures. אף על פי ששמותיהן כשמות
עובדי כוכבים כשרים מפני שרוב ישראל שבחוצה לארץ שמותיהן כשמות עובדי כוכבים
*Af al pi she-shmoteihen ki-shmotei ovdei kochavim kesherim, mipnei she-rov Yisrael she-be-chutz
la-aretz shmoteihen ki-shmotei ovdei kochavim*. Even if the names are non-Jewish names,
they're still good because the majority, one doesn't know if it literally
means majority, but whatever, you know, a large percentage of Jews outside
of Israel have non-Jewish names. And therefore if a גט *get* comes
with non-Jewish names, you know, what's the likelihood that this was a
גט *get* signed by non-Jews? You know, they're so it's so prevalent
for Jews to have non-Jewish names, of course we're going to assume
that these are Jews and that they just had non-Jewish names. So
you see this goes against what רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said, because
this says that you can assume that they're Jews even if they're
not blatantly non-Jewish names, you can still your assumption should be that
they were signed by Jews. So the גמרא *Gemara* says התם כדתני
טעמא *Hatam kidtani ta'ama*. No, that doesn't challenge רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*.
There it makes it clear why that's okay. מפני שרוב ישראל שבחוצה
לארץ שמותיהן כשמות עובדי כוכבים *Mipnei she-rov Yisrael she-be-chutz la-aretz shmoteihen ki-shmotei
ovdei kochavim*. That's when they're coming from outside of Israel. And outside
of Israel, particularly חוצה לארץ *Chutz la-aretz* doesn't mean בבל *Bavel*, and
it's a place, you know, of more integration with a larger society
and so on and a less of a sort of like a
rabbinic presence. There, okay, it's obviously these, you know, your normal assumption
is a גט *get* signed by Jews. And the fact that it's
non-Jewish names coming from a place where Jews, very prevalent, have non-Jewish
names, it's all going to be fine. Okay. But from within Israel,
you know, it's not so prevalent that Jews have these names, and
in that case we have to be concerned that it's signed by
non-Jews. Alright. ואיכא דאמרי *V'ika d'amri*, and others say, כי מתניתא בעא
מיניה פשט ליה ממתניתא *Ki matnita ba'a mineih pashat lei mi-matnita*. No,
the question was exactly the case of the תוספתא *Tosefta*, when they
came from חוצה לארץ *Chutz la-aretz*. What's the story? And רבי יוחנן's
*Rabbi Yochanan's* response was, oh, when they come from חוצה לארץ *Chutz
la-aretz*, from מדינת הים *Medinat ha-yam*, then even non-Jewish sounding names, you
know, we can go ahead and assume that they're Jews because that's
the nature of Jews in חוצה לארץ *Chutz la-aretz* they have those
names, and therefore it's all fine. Okay. The fascinating thing about this
whole גמרא *Gemara* is the recognition without any sort of critical comment
that how prevalent it was for Jews to have non-Jewish sounding names,
or non-Jewish names we should just say. There's an amazing תשובה Teshuvah
*teshuva* in רב משה פיינשטיין *Rav Moshe Feinstein* in אגרות משה *Igrot
Moshe* where somebody said to him, you know, we should criticize all
those people who... You know, so prevalent to be
give Jewish babies
secular names. I was given, my generation, everybody was given like a
secular name and a Jewish name, right? So he said we should
criticize this, you know, because the גמרא says that the reason that
the Jews were saved from Egypt, the Israelites were saved, was because
they didn't change their names and their dress and their language. So,
how are we so okay with everybody giving גוישע Goyishe names? So,
you know, and it's very funny, right, the גמרא here sort of
recognizes it was extremely prevalent. Anyway, so Rav Moshe in his תשובה
basically goes through all the תנאים, Tannaim, all the אמוראים, Amoraim, all
the אחרונים, Achronim, ראשונים, Rishonim, who had secular names. And he said,
look, you know, this was completely totally acceptable. And he said, what
about this מדרש? Medrash? And here he says a brilliant thing. He
says, that מדרש Medrash was talking
before
מתן תורה. Matan Torah. And before מתן תורה, Matan Torah, the only
thing they had to maintain their identity was these external markers, right?
Language, names, the way they dressed. You needed those markers to maintain
their identity. And that's what it means that they were saved because
they were able to hold on to their identity. After מתן תורה,
Matan Torah, says Rav Moshe, we have תריג מצוות. Taryag Mitzvos. So
we do not need to so worry about whether the names are
Jewish or not Jewish. Our תריג מצוות Taryag Mitzvos maintains and sustains
our identity. And that, and for that זכות Zchus we could be
נגאלו. Nigalu. All right. So we'll end with this and pick up
on דף, for דף יב Daf Yud Bais tomorrow.